I'd like you all
أريد منكم جميعاً
to ask yourselves a question
أن تسألوا أنفسكم سؤالاً
which you may never have asked yourselves before:
لم تسألوه أنفسكم من قبل
What is possible with the human voice?
ماهو الممكن من صوت الإنسان؟
(Beatboxing)
(البيت بوكس) *نوع من أنواع الإيقاع الصوتي ويعتمد على تقليد أصوات آلات النقر والإيقاع وأصوات الآلات الموسيقية عن طريق الفم أو اللسان أو الشفتين
♪ Ooh baby ♪
♪ يا حبيبتي ♪
♪ baby ♪
♪ حبيبتي ♪
♪ baby ♪ (Baby crying)
♪ حبيبتي ♪ (طفل يبكي)
♪ baby ♪ (Cat meowing)
♪ حبيبتي ♪ (مواء قطة)
(Dog barking)
(نباح كلب)
Yeah.
نعم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
(Boomerang noises)
(أصوات)
It was coming straight for me. I had to. It was, yeah.
لقد كانت قادمة من أجلي فكان علي فعل ذلك، كانت.. نعم
As you can probably well imagine,
فكما يمكنكم تخيله
I was a strange child.
كنت طفلاً غريباً
(Laughter)
(قهقهة)
Because the thing is, I was constantly trying
فالحقيقة هي أنني كنت أحاول بإستمرار
to extend my repertoire of noises to be
أن أوسع مجموعة الأصوات الممكنة
the very maximum that it could be.
لأقصى درجة يمكن وصولها
I was constantly experimenting with these noises.
كنت أجرب هذه الأصوات بإستمرار
And I'm still on that mission.
وما زلت أفعل هذه المهمة
I'm still trying to find every noise
ما زلت أحاول إيجاد كل الأصوات
that I can possibly make.
التي يمكنني إصدارها
And the thing is, I'm a bit older and wiser now,
لكنني الآن أكبر عمراً وأكثر حكمة
and I know that there's some noises
وأعلم أن هنالك بعض الأصوات
I'll never be able to make because I'm hemmed in
التي لا يمكنني إخراجها لأنني مقيد
by my physical body, and there's things it can't do.
بجسدي وأن هنالك أشياء لا يمكنه فعلها
And there's things that no one's voice can do.
وهنالك أشياء لا يمكن لأي صوت فعلها
For example, no one can do two notes at the same time.
على سبيل المثاال: لا يمكن لأي شخص إصدار نغمتين في الوقت نفسه
You can do two-tone singing,
يمكنك الغناء بصوتين مختلفين
which monks can do, which is like...
وهذا ما يستطيع فعله الرهبان، وهو مثل...
(Two-tone singing)
(غناء بصوتين مختلفي النبرة في نفس الوقت)
But that's cheating.
لكنه غش
And it hurts your throat.
ويضر حلقك
So there's things you can't do, and these limitations
إذا هنالك أشياء لا يمكنك فعلها وهذه الحدود
on the human voice have always really annoyed me,
في صوت الإنسان لطالما أزعجتني
because beatbox is the best way of getting
لأن البيت بوكس هو أفضل طريقة لنقل
musical ideas out of your head and into the world,
الأفكار الموسيقية التي في مخيلتك إلى العالم
but they're sketches at best,
ولكن هذه الأفكار هي مقطوعات موسيقية غير موزونة
which is what's annoyed me.
وهذا بحد ذاته ما يزعجي.
If only, if only there was a way
لكن ماذا لو كان هناك طريقة
for these ideas to come out unimpeded
لتخرج هذه الأفكار دون أي عائق
by the restrictions which my body gives it.
من القيود التي تحتمها علي جسدي.
So I've been working with these guys,
كنت أعمل مع بعض من الرجال
and we've made a machine.
وأخترعنا جهازاً
We've made a system which is basically
وقمنا بإنشاء نظام الذي هو في الأساس
a live production machine,
بمثابة آلة إنتاج فورية
a real-time music production machine,
آلة إنتاج موسيقى حقيقية
and it enables me to, using nothing but my voice,
وتمكتني من استخدام صوتي فقط
create music in real time as I hear it in my head
خلق الموسيقى على الواقع كما أسمعه في مخيلتي
unimpeded by any physical restrictions
دون عوائق من أي قيود جسدية
that my body might place on me.
قد يفرضها علي جسدي
And I'm going to show you what it can do.
وسوف أريكم ما يمكن لهذه الآلة فعله
And before I start making noises with it,
وقبل البدء في صنع الأصوات منها
and using it to manipulate my voice,
واستخدامها للتلاعب بصوتي
I want to reiterate that everything that you're about to hear
أريد أن أؤكد من جديد أن كل ما أنتم على وشك سماعه
is being made by my voice.
هو من صوتي
This system has --
ولهذا النظام
thank you, beautiful assistant --
شكرا لك، أيتها المساعدة الجميلة
this system has no sounds in it itself
لا يحتوي هذا النظام لأي صوت
until I start putting sounds in it,
إلا عندما أبدئ في وضع الأصوات فيه
so there's no prerecorded samples of any kind.
أي لا يوجد أي من النماذج الصوتية المسجلة مسبقاً
So once this thing really gets going,
وعند بدء ذلك بالعمل
and it really starts to mangle the audio I'm putting into it,
ويبدأ فعلياً بالتلاعب بالصوت الذي أضعه فيه
but it is, so I'm going to take you through it bit by bit
ولكنه صوتاً بشرياً، لذلك سأقوم بتجربة ذلك معكم خطوة بخطوة
and start nice and simple.
ببداية جميلة وسهلة
So the polyphony problem: I've only got one voice.
لذا فمشكلة تعدد الأصوات هي: كوني أملك صوتا واحدا فقط.
How do I get around the problem
كيف يمكنني حل هذه المشكلة؟
of really wanting to have as many different voices
مشكلة الرغبة بالحصول على الكثير من الأصوات المختلفة
going on at the same time.
في نفس الوقت
The simplest way to do it is something like this.
وأبسط طريقة لعمل ذلك هي
(Beatboxing)
(بيتبوكسينج)
By dancing. It's like this.
بالرقص، مثل ذلك
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Thanks.
شكرا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So that's probably the easiest way.
هذه تقريباً أسهل طريقة موجودة
But if you want to do something a little bit more immediate,
ولكن إذا كنت تريد عمل شيئا سريعا بعض الشيء
something that you can't achieve with live looping,
شيئا لا يمكنك تحقيقة بإستخدام حلقات حية
there's other ways to layer your voice up.
هنالك طرق أخرى لرفع خامة صوتك لمستوى أعلى
There's things like pitch-shifting,
هنالك طرق مثل التغيير المستمر لنبرة الصوت
which are awesome,
وهو ما أعتبره رائعاً!
and I'm going to show you now what that sounds like.
وسوف أسمعكم ما أقصده
So I'm going to start another beat for you, like this.
لذا سأقوم بإخراج صوتا آخرا لكم مثل ذلك
(Beatboxing)
(بيتبوكسينج)
There's always got to be a bit of a dance at the start,
لابد أن يكون هناك بعضا من الرقص في البداية
because it's just fun, so
لان الغرض من ذلك هو المتعة، لذا
you can clap along if you want.
يمكنكم التصفيق أثناء ذلك كيفما تشائون
You don't have to. It's fine. Check it out.
ولكن ذلك ليس بضروري، استمع لهذا
I'm going to lay down a bass sound now.
سوف أقوم بإخراج صوت جهير
(Music)
(موسيقى)
And now, a rockabilly guitar.
والآن، غيتار الروكابيلي
Which is nice. But what if I want to make, say, a -- (Applause) --
وهو جميل. ولكن ماذا لو كنت أريد إخراج صوت، -(تصفيق)-
Thanks. What if I want to make, say, a rock organ?
شكرا. ماذا لو كنت أريد إخراج صوت جهاز روك؟
Is that possible? Yes, it is,
هل هذا ممكن؟ نعم إنه كذلك
by recording myself like this.
بتسجيل نفسي مثل هذا.
(Organ sound)
(جهاز الصوت)
And now I have that, I have that recorded.
والآن لدي هذا مسجلا
Assign it to a keyboard.
وبتعيينه للوحة المفاتيح
(Music)
(موسيقى)
So that's cool.
هذا ممتاز!
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
But what if I wanted to sound like the whole of Pink Floyd?
ولكن ماذا لو أردت أن أبدو مثل جميع فريق "بينك فلويد"؟
Impossible, you say. No.
تقولون مستحيل؟ لا
It is possible, and you can do it very simply
إنه ممكناً، ويمكنك القيام بذلك ببساطة شديدة
using this machine. It's really fantastic. Check it out.
باستخدام هذا الجهاز، أنه حقاً رائع. استمعوا لذلك
(Music)
(موسيقى)
So every noise you can hear there is my voice.
اذا أي صوت يمكنك سماعه الآن هو صوتي
I didn't just trigger something which sounds like that.
لم أقم بفعل أي شيء ليبدو كذلك
There's no samples. There's no synthesizers.
لا يوجد أي نماذج صوتيه أو لا يوجد أي نوع من التأليف الموسيقي
and when you get to that point, you have to ask, don't you,
وعندما نصل إلى هذه النقطة، عليك أن تسأل، أليس كذلك؟
what's the point?
ما هو الهدف من ذلك؟
Why do this? (Laughter)
لماذا تفعل هذا؟ (ضحك)
Because it's cheaper than hiring the whole of Pink Floyd,
لأن ذلك يعد أرخص من التعاقد مع كل من فرقة "بينك فلويد" الموسيقية،
I suppose, is the easy answer.
علي ما أعتقد، هو الإجابة البديهية
But in actual fact, I haven't made this machine
ولكن في الواقع الفعلي، لم أقم بإختراع هذا الجهاز
so that I can emulate things that already exist.
لكي أقلد أشياءً موجودة بالفعل.
I've made this so that I can make
لقد أخترعتها لكي أصنع
any noise that I can imagine.
أي صوت يمكنني تخيله
So with your permission, I'm going to do
فمن بعد أذنكم، سوف أقوم
some things that are in my mind,
بجعلكم تستمعون لأصوات تدور في مخيلتي
and I hope you enjoy them,
وآمل أن تستمتعوا بها
because they're rather unusual,
لأنها غير عادية
especially when you're doing things which are
خاصة عندما تفعل اشياء
as unusual as this, it can be hard to believe
غير عادية كهذه، يكون من الصعب التصديق
that it is all my voice, you see.
بأنها جميعها من صوتي، استمعوا
(Voice effects)
(المؤثرات الصوتية)
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Like this.
مثل ذلك
So, loosely defined,
لذا، لو عرفنا ذلك بسهولة
that is what's possible with the human voice.
هذا ما يمكن للصوت البشري فعله!
Thank you very much, ladies and gentlemen.
شكرا جزيلا، أيها السيدات والسادة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)